<Lessons>
<Topics>
	<Help>Yes</Help>
	<Menu>Yes</Menu>
	<Resource>Yes</Resource>
	<Exit>Yes</Exit>
	<Glossary>Yes</Glossary>
	<CourseName><![CDATA[<b>Back to Basics—Pricing Module</b>]]></CourseName>		
		<!-- Lessson 0 -->
		<MLesson>
				<LessonName>Overview</LessonName>				
					<Topic>
					<TopicName>How Will this Training Help?</TopicName>
						<Pages>					
								<Page>
									<PageName>topic_01/T1_page02.swf</PageName>
									<PageType>Animation</PageType>						
									<Slider>Yes</Slider>	
									<Audio>Yes</Audio>
									<NextButton>Yes</NextButton>
									<TranscriptText><![CDATA[We all may find ourselves in Tim’s shoes sometimes.<br>Getting the pricing strategy right is a mix of a lot of factors such as, reacting to demand, knowing the customer side of the story, understanding how prices are dependent on each other or seeing how our Best Flex Rate is the core of our pricing strategy. It includes utilizing the tools and principles set up at IHG to help Revenue Leaders make the right decisions.<br>At the end of this course you will be able to carry out a self-audit of your current rate structure, have the right tools, follow the pricing principles and understand the customer side of your pricing strategy. You will also understand your competition better, be more reactive and know when to change your strategy, measure price sensitivity and get your pricing right every day.<br>In this training we will meet three Revenue Leaders: Tim, Laura and Parker. We will learn about their pricing mistakes, best practices and strategies. Let’s begin with Tim’s story.]]></TranscriptText>																			
								</Page>	
						</Pages>
					</Topic>
				</MLesson>
				<MLesson>
				<LessonName>Pricing Principles</LessonName>
					<Topic>
					<TopicName>Pricing Principle 1</TopicName>
						<Pages>					
								<Page>
									<PageName>topic_01/T1_page03.swf</PageName>
									<PageType>Animation</PageType>						
									<Slider>Yes</Slider>	
									<Audio>Yes</Audio>
									<NextButton>Yes</NextButton>
									<TranscriptText><![CDATA[The first principle of pricing at IHG says that the—Best Flex Rate (BFR) is your market appropriate rate.<br>Last year, Tim kept his BFR at a constant rate of $130.<br>Instead of adjusting the BFR, he offered several promotions.<br>This jeopardized the BFR and the Advance Purchase efficiency of his hotel during the holiday season.<br>This strategy also displaced high paying customers to the promotion.<br>Such a pricing strategy educates the guest to wait and or look for promotions, and has the effect to postpone the act of making the reservation. ]]></TranscriptText>																			
								</Page>	
						</Pages>
					</Topic>
					<Topic>
					<TopicName>Need for Best Flex Rates</TopicName>
						<Pages>					
								<Page>
									<PageName>topic_01/T1_page04.swf</PageName>
									<PageType>Animation</PageType>						
									<Slider>Yes</Slider>	
									<Audio>Yes</Audio>
									<NextButton>Yes</NextButton>
									<TranscriptText><![CDATA[Understanding how to use Best Flex Rate (BFR) is one of the ways that hotels can maximize revenue through our pricing products. So why do we have a Best Flexible Rate?<br>Earlier a rack rate was used, which was the premium rate offered.<br>However, this was not utilized by the hotels, except as a false benchmark.<ul><li>As customers became savvier and got access to several hotel rates, the rack rate was used less and less.</li><li>Rack rate did not take into account the demand for a hotel, therefore was irrational.</li></ul>To overcome these short-comings the Best Flex Rate was introduced. BFR:<ul><li>Is simple to execute for the hotel</li><li>Is easy to understand for the guest</li><li>Gives the hotel the flexibility to take demand into account</li></ul>By correctly managing BFR, hotels are able to maximize revenue and to improve profit.]]></TranscriptText>																			
								</Page>	
						</Pages>
					</Topic>
					<Topic>
					<TopicName>BFR—Points to Remember</TopicName>
						<Pages>					
								<Page>
									<PageName>topic_01/T1_page05.swf</PageName>
									<PageType>Animation</PageType>						
									<Slider>Yes</Slider>	
									<Audio>Yes</Audio>
									<NextButton>Yes</NextButton>
									<TranscriptText><![CDATA[Tim did not account for the fact that the demand for his hotel rooms in this season would be high.<br>Instead, he got pressurized to give unreasonable promotions, seeing his competitors.<br>Keeping the BFR rate constant for the entire season brought Tim’s RevPAR below the market average.<br>BFR should be a mix of: <ul><li>Demand</li><li>Forecast</li><li>Competition</li><li>Value</li></ul>In good times (when you forecast strong demand, like in Tim’s case, during the holiday season), increase the BFR. In bad times, reduce the BFR to increase occupancy. You can use tools, such as PERFORM to set a good BFR at all times.<br>Ask yourself these questions to do a self-audit.]]></TranscriptText>																			
								</Page>	
						</Pages>
					</Topic>
					<Topic>
					<TopicName>Pricing Principle 2</TopicName>
						<Pages>					
								<Page>
									<PageName>topic_01/T1_page06.swf</PageName>
									<PageType>Animation</PageType>						
									<Slider>Yes</Slider>	
									<Audio>Yes</Audio>
									<NextButton>Yes</NextButton>
									<TranscriptText><![CDATA[The next principle of pricing at IHG says that discounts off your Best Flexible Rate are fine, but should carry restrictions.<br>Tim had offered promotions and discounts off his Best Flex Rate, at the last hour, without any restrictions.<br>The promotions were very confusing and the customers couldn’t tell one offer from the other. The lack of clarity deterred customers from booking.<br>The lack of clarity deterred customers from booking.<br>For a few high paying customers, these were a bonus, while they would’ve readily paid higher rates.<br>Families that booked early felt penalized by the last minute discounts and promotions.<br>In retrospect Tim realized that this had affected customer perception of price integrity. It had also affected the ADR negatively and had pushed back occupancy due to customer confusion.]]></TranscriptText>																			
								</Page>	
						</Pages>
					</Topic>
					<Topic>
					<TopicName>Importance of Trade-offs</TopicName>
						<Pages>					
								<Page>
									<PageName>topic_01/T1_page07.swf</PageName>
									<PageType>Animation</PageType>						
									<Slider>Yes</Slider>	
									<Audio>Yes</Audio>
									<NextButton>Yes</NextButton>
									<TranscriptText><![CDATA[Trade-offs are required to create a win-win for the guest and for the hotel. Trade-offs include the willingness to: <ul><li>Pre-pay</li><li>Book in advance</li><li>Stay for a specific period of time</li><li>Stay over certain days</li></ul>The more we move closer to the day of arrival, the discount lessens.<br>Getting the base bookings in advance means that you have more flexibility with BFR closer to the time of arrival.<br>If you find that due to the base booking your hotel is filling up, then there is an opportunity to drive your Average Daily Rate (ADR).]]></TranscriptText>																			
								</Page>	
						</Pages>
					</Topic>
					<Topic>
					<TopicName>Tim Uses no Fencing</TopicName>
						<Pages>					
								<Page>
									<PageName>topic_01/T1_page08.swf</PageName>
									<PageType>SelfCheck</PageType>						
									<Slider>Yes</Slider>	
									<Audio>Yes</Audio>
									<NextButton>Yes</NextButton>
									<TranscriptText><![CDATA[Tim's promotions came with little fencing. Customers got good offers, without any trade-offs.<br>For example, customers could book at a discount and get a free spa voucher.<br>It was almost the end of the season when Tim added that customers needed to book for at least three nights to avail this offer.<br>Things, however, became worse because he did not update the details on Holidex plus.<br>So what was Tim’s mistake last season?<br>Make a list of Tim’s mistakes and click the question to see the answer.<br>Tim made many mistakes in pricing. Do you have any of these points on your list?]]></TranscriptText>																			
								</Page>	
						</Pages>
					</Topic>
					<Topic>
					<TopicName>Tim’s Ideal Approach</TopicName>
						<Pages>					
								<Page>
									<PageName>topic_01/T1_page09.swf</PageName>
									<PageType>Animation</PageType>						
									<Slider>Yes</Slider>	
									<Audio>Yes</Audio>
									<NextButton>Yes</NextButton>
									<TranscriptText><![CDATA[Tim must look at his current reservation booking window to set the right lead-time.<br>The advance purchase helps lock-in the business early. We have to make sure we are not cannibalizing from people who could have bought BFR but got offered advance purchase instead.<br>Tim’s current lead-time for the hotel is 10 days therefore having an advance purchase at 7 days will displace three days of potential bookings from BFR. Instead having it at 15 days or more will encourage the customer to book earlier.<br>Ask yourself these questions to do a self-audit.]]></TranscriptText>																			
								</Page>	
						</Pages>
					</Topic>
					<Topic>
					<TopicName>Pricing Principle 3</TopicName>
						<Pages>					
								<Page>
									<PageName>topic_01/T1_page10.swf</PageName>
									<PageType>Animation</PageType>						
									<Slider>Yes</Slider>	
									<Audio>Yes</Audio>
									<NextButton>Yes</NextButton>
									<TranscriptText><![CDATA[The third principle of pricing asks us to consider impacts to all market segments when making pricing decisions.<br>Unfortunately, Tim flouted this principle too. He realized only later that by using heavy discount and promotions during the peak season, he had negatively affected the corporate segment.<br>His corporate customers checked other rates, and suddenly the corporate rates they had received looked unattractive to them.<br>This time over Tim was going to be more careful. He was asking himself these questions:<ul><li>How is my pricing decision affecting other market segments?</li><li>Am I too flexible?</li><li>Am I too competitive?</li><li>Am I protecting each segment’s fencing and price point?</li></ul>]]></TranscriptText>																			
								</Page>	
						</Pages>
					</Topic>
					<Topic>
					<TopicName>Looking at All Segments</TopicName>
						<Pages>					
								<Page>
									<PageName>topic_01/T1_page11.swf</PageName>
									<PageType>Animation</PageType>						
									<Slider>Yes</Slider>	
									<Audio>Yes</Audio>
									<NextButton>Yes</NextButton>
									<TranscriptText><![CDATA[A poor practice is to look at pricing in “segment silos”—focusing on one segment at a time without much thought about how the segments interact and impact each other.<br>Always remember that the pricing of ALL other segments is calculated on the basis of your BFR.<br>That is why BFR is the core of your pricing strategy. While pricing take into account all market segments as change in one will always impact others.<br>Ask yourself this question to do a self-audit.<br>Look at the rate card to know all the segments you must consider while deciding the pricing.<br>You can download the rate card on MERLIN in the IHG Revenue Room, in the Pricing Corner.]]></TranscriptText>																			
								</Page>	
						</Pages>
					</Topic>
					<Topic>
					<TopicName>Pricing Principle 4</TopicName>
						<Pages>					
								<Page>
									<PageName>topic_01/T1_page12.swf</PageName>
									<PageType>Animation</PageType>						
									<Slider>Yes</Slider>	
									<Audio>Yes</Audio>
									<NextButton>Yes</NextButton>
									<TranscriptText><![CDATA[The fourth principle states that you must flex your discounts and room type to encourage buy-ups.<br>Tim had given discount on a room only offer. Instead one of the alternatives could have been to package smaller room discount with another element (such as breakfast).<br>This kind of a discount would’ve shown value to the customer and would have been beneficial for the hotel.<br>The packaged offer must be significantly more attractive than buying the different elements separately to encourage the customer to buy this offer. This will generate higher total revenue for the hotel.]]></TranscriptText>																			
								</Page>	
						</Pages>
					</Topic>
					<Topic>
					<TopicName>Encouraging Buy-Ups</TopicName>
						<Pages>					
								<Page>
									<PageName>topic_01/T1_page13.swf</PageName>
									<PageType>SelfCheck</PageType>						
									<Slider>Yes</Slider>	
									<Audio>Yes</Audio>
									<NextButton>Yes</NextButton>
									<TranscriptText><![CDATA[To encourage buy-ups in your hotel you can provide:<ul><li>IHG Reward Points</li><li>Customized Packages</li><li>Different Room Types</li><li>Supplements</li></ul>Click each buy-up option type to learn more about it.<br>To ensure that we encourage buy-ups from our guests it is important to remember to compress rates.<br>Ask yourself these questions to do a self-audit.]]></TranscriptText>																			
								</Page>	
						</Pages>
					</Topic>
					<Topic>
					<TopicName>Pricing Principle 5</TopicName>
						<Pages>					
								<Page>
									<PageName>topic_01/T1_page14.swf</PageName>
									<PageType>Animation</PageType>						
									<Slider>Yes</Slider>	
									<Audio>Yes</Audio>
									<NextButton>Yes</NextButton>
									<TranscriptText><![CDATA[The fifth principle reminds us to clearly communicate rate descriptions.<br>Tim remembered how he had not communicated that customers needed to book for at least three nights to avail a free spa voucher.<br>This had led to several angry customers who were unaware of this requirement and had been disgruntled when they went to the spa and were asked to pay up.<br>Let’s look at a few examples:<ul><li>Tick meal plan indicator on the rate category</li><li>Include the wording that breakfast is included in the rate category description for BB rates (first 47 characters only show in GDS)</li><li>Use expanded description on customised rate categories</li></ul>Ask yourself these questions to do a self-audit.]]></TranscriptText>																			
								</Page>	
						</Pages>
					</Topic>
					<Topic>
					<TopicName>Topic Summary </TopicName>
						<Pages>					
								<Page>
									<PageName>topic_01/T1_page15.swf</PageName>
									<PageType>Animation</PageType>						
									<Slider>Yes</Slider>	
									<Audio>Yes</Audio>
									<NextButton>Yes</NextButton>
									<TranscriptText><![CDATA[This year Tim plans to be more cautious and to clearly communicate all details to the customers via his Website.<br>Here’s a list of principles that Tim will remember while pricing for the holiday season:<br>Principle 1: Best Flexible Rate (BFR) is your market appropriate rate.<br>Principle 2: Discounts off your Best Flexible Rate are fine, but should carry restrictions.<br>Principle 3: Consider impacts to all market segments when making pricing decisions.<br>Principle 4: Flex your discounts and room type to encourage buy-ups.<br>Principle 5: Clearly communicate rate descriptions.]]></TranscriptText>																			
								</Page>	
						</Pages>
					</Topic>
				</MLesson>
				

</Lessons>
